Caroline Stratton, PhD

caroline.stratton@utexas.edu | +1 (541) 231-8825

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Technology interventions for social good, ICT4D, ICTs and organizing

My research poses and responds to pressing questions about how organizations may effectively design and implement technology interventions for social good. My analytic approach integrates theory from and contributes to multiple disciplines, including communication studies, organization studies, and information systems. I have experience in team ethnography methods, comparative studies, and international fieldwork.

ACADEMIC EMPLOYMENT

University of Texas School of Information - Austin, TX, USA

Postdoctoral Fellow, 2019 - 2020

Supervisors: Dr. James Howison, Dr. Diane Bailey (Cornell University)

EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS

Doctor of Philosophy in Information Studies, awarded May 2018

The University of Texas at Austin

Dissertation title: Orientation to Practice and Organizational Relationships in ICT4D: An Emerging Theory of

Tie and Network Formation

Committee: Dr. Diane Bailey (advisor and chair), Dr. James Howison, Dr. Kenneth Fleischmann,

Dr. Joseph Straubhaar

Bachelor of Science in Nuclear and Radiological Engineering, awarded May 2009

Georgia Institute of Technology

President's Scholarship Recipient

PUBLICATIONS

4 journal articles, 5 peer-reviewed conference papers, 3 conference presentations

JOURNAL ARTICLES

1. **C. Stratton**, D. Bailey, & P. Leonardi. (forthcoming). Translating national discourse into teaching and learning outcomes: Portability and connectivity in developing countries' ICT in education (ICT4E) initiatives. *New Media and Society*.

- 2. **C. Stratton** & D. Nemer. (conditionally accepted). ICTD in Latin America: Literature review, scholar feedback, and recommendations. *Information Technology for Development*.
- 3. R. Grace, **C. Stratton**, & F. Fonseca. (2019). Content matters: How online language content gives rise to digital divides. *Social Science Quarterly*, 100(6), 1999-2016.
- 4. S. Buchanan, **C. Stratton**, Y. Sun, & A. Chaudhary. (2017). Survey research on tasks and competencies to inform records management education. *Records Management Journal*, *27*(1), 2-18.

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- 1. **C. Stratton**. January 2018. Inverting the relationship between development and public access computing (PAC): A comparative study of PAC ecosystems. In *Proceedings of the 51st Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences*.
- 2. **C. Stratton** & R. Grace. October 2016. Exploring linguistic diversity of MOOCs: Implications for international development. In *Proceedings of the 2016 Annual Meeting of the Association for Information Science & Technology*. Copenhagen, Denmark.
- 3. **C. Stratton**, D. Sholler, D. Bailey, P. Leonardi, & C. Rodríguez-Lluesma. June 2016. Competing institutional logics in ICT4D education projects: A South American study. In *Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development (ICTD).* Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA.
- 4. **C. Stratton** & D. Bailey. March 2015. A turn to Latin America: Improving theory development in the ICT4D literature. Preliminary results paper in *Proceedings of the iConference*. Newport Beach, California, USA.
- 5. D. Sholler & **C. Stratton**. March 2015. Managing without authority: Records managers in interorganizational contexts. Preliminary results paper in *Proceedings of the iConference*. Newport Beach, California, USA.

ACCEPTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

- 1. **C. Stratton**. October 2016. How small efforts might become big: A grounded study of organizational networks in ICT4D. Organizational Communication Mini Conference. Department of Communication, Northwestern University. Evanston, IL, USA.
- 2. **C. Stratton** & D. Bailey. August 2016. An exploration of innovation outside of the R&D lab: The colloquial usage of innovation and provocations for studying innovation. Annual Meeting of the Society for Social Studies of Science (4S). Barcelona, Spain.

3. **C. Stratton** & D. Bailey. August 2014. The unfavored region: The absence of Latin America in ICT4D research. Annual Meeting of the Society for Social Studies of Science (4S). Buenos Aires, Argentina.

JOURNAL SUBMISSIONS UNDER REVIEW

1. C. Stratton. Title suppressed for double blind review. (Under first round review, July 2019). *The Information Society*.

JOURNAL SUBMISSIONS IN PREPARATION

- 1. C. Stratton, D. Bailey, & P. Leonardi. Multiple pathways to development: Co-existing organizing visions of ICT in development. Target: *MIS Quarterly*.
- 2. C. Stratton. Characterizing demand-pull for ultra-fast broadband: Examining intended uses among public service organizations. Target: *Telecommunications Policy*.

HONORS AND AWARDS

Best Reviewer, Academy of Management, Organizational Communication and Information Systems (OCIS) division, 2017

Honorable Mention for extended abstract and poster, HCI Across Borders Symposium, 2017 Donald D. Harrington PhD Fellowship, University of Texas full PhD scholarship, 2012-2017, \$49,000 per year

Benonine Muse Scholarship, School of Information, 2015-2016, \$3000

Layton B. Murphy Scholarship, School of Information, 2013-2015, \$3000

COMPETITIVE COLLOQUIA AND WORKSHOPS

- 1. Social Technologies for Digital Wellbeing Among Marginalized Communities workshop at CSCW 2019, participant. Austin, TX, USA, November 2019.
- 2. HCI Across Borders Symposium at CHI 2017, presenter (poster received honorable mention). D. Nemer & C. Stratton. Where's ICT for Latin America? Addressing the research gap in ICT4D literature. Denver, CO, USA, May 2017.
- 3. Association for Information Science & Technology Doctoral Colloquium, participant. Copenhagen, Denmark, October 2016.
- 4. Academy of Management, Organizational Communication & Information Systems Doctoral Consortium, participant. Anaheim, CA, USA, August 2016.

- 5. Summer Institute of the Consortium for the Science of Sociotechnical Systems, participant. Stevenson, WA, USA, June 2016.
- 6. iConference 2016 Doctoral Colloquium, participant. Philadelphia, PA, USA, March 2016.

SERVICE AND ADMINISTRATIVE EXPERIENCE

Associate Editor for 2020 Joint Conference of IFIP Working Groups 8.2, 9.1, and 9.4. The future of digital work: The challenge of inequality.

Ad hoc reviews

Journals: *The Information Society, Journal of Strategic Information Systems* Conferences: AMCIS (2014), HICSS (2015, 2017), Academy of Management OCIS Division (2016, 2017*), iConference (2017, 2018, 2020)

Diversity & Inclusion Committee of the School of Information, 2018 – collaborated with faculty, staff, and student colleagues to establish events and initiatives that promoted an inclusive climate in the School of Information

Student Association of the School of Information, 2016-2017 – served as faculty liaison, appointed students to school committees, conducted orientation activities for new students

School of Information IT Task Force, 2014-2015 – revised school policies regarding faculty and staff computer purchasing, classroom technology equipment, graduate student computing resources

EXPERIENCE

Austin Free-Net - Austin, TX, USA

Digital Literacy Program Manager, 2018 - 2019

Managed a social service program funded by the City of Austin's Digital Inclusion Office to provide underserved populations with access to computers and internet, as well as training about how to use these technologies. Set the strategy for the program, managed the operation of 10 technology public access and training sites across Austin, oversaw curriculum development and instruction, and maintained responsibility for the achievement of funders' desired outputs and outcomes. Identified and responded to community needs for digital literacy, determined how to incorporate emerging technologies in the program, and sought funding for programmatic and organizational sustainability. Obtained \$50,000 in funding through grant and contract opportunities.

Achieving Development Goals with Information Technology, National Science Foundation Grant IIS-1412924, \$1.4M four-year grant

^{*} received best reviewer award

Co-PIs: Drs. Diane Bailey, Paul Leonardi

Graduate Research Assistant, 2014 - 2018

Located and negotiated initial access to field research sites in four South American countries. Aided in writing grant proposal. Designed semi-structured interview protocols. Independently conducted ethnographic observation, focus groups, and semi-structured interviews in Bolivia (full time for three months) and Colombia (full time for three months). Aided graduate research assistants in preparing to do fieldwork, oversaw student assistants in transcription and translation of recorded data, managed data storage. Planned and carried out collaborative team writing projects.

University of Texas School of Information - Austin, TX, USA

Teaching Assistant, 2013 - 2014

Provided technology instruction in lecture, group, and individual modalities to graduate students as an Information Technology Lab teaching assistant (Summer 2013 - Fall 2014). Planned, managed, and delivered trainings on basic programming and Web design. Aided instructor's class preparation and delivered lectures to graduate students for INF 380C, Managing Information Organizations (Fall 2014).

University of Texas School of Information - Austin, TX, USA

Teaching Intern, 2014

Created materials for a new course, Geographical Information Systems for ICT4D Applications. Developed a syllabus, lesson plans, and course materials under supervision of a pedagogy instructor.

Exelon Corporation - Kennett Square, PA, USA

Nuclear Engineer, 2009 - 2012

Managed two 20 month-long projects to refuel nuclear reactors. Performed nuclear fuel design simulations and created evaluations to justify designs. Developed and revised procedures for the Nuclear Fuels group to refine and standardize work processes.

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

Association for Information Science & Technology (ASIS&T)

LANGUAGES AND SKILLS

Spanish: fluent in speaking, reading, and writing

Statistical and Geographical: Stata, SPSS, UCINET, NetDraw

Design and Programming: Adobe Illustrator, InDesign, HTML, CSS, MATLAB, Python